Hello, I'm Serzen Patel.
In this video, we will be showing
you how to use a binocular indirect
ophthalmoscope or BIO.
The main use of a BIO is to perform a fundus examination.
It allows
the user to see a wide stereoscopic field of view or 3D view of
the back of the eye.
When scleral indentation is used, you can also get quick and dynamic views of
the far periphery
of the retina.
This is important in patients complaining of flashes or floaters who may
have developed a retinal tear as well as premature babies for judging the stage of retinopathy
or prematurity.
Another big benefit of the BIO is that it allows a good view of
the retina despite immediate
opacity such as corneal scarring, cataract or even blood in the vitreous.
It is also mobile and easy to carry around.
It can therefore be used to examine patients with poor mobility such as patients who are
wheelchair bound or bed bound.
For less cooperative patients such as babies and young children, you can usually still get
good idea of the back of the eye if it's healthy or not with a brief view.
Place the
BIO on your head making sure it's comfortable and secure so that it does
not move when you're
examining.
You can see us adjusting it here.
Turn the light on and check that the beam is aligned with your line of sight.
So you're
able to see your thumb singly at arm's length and it's in the centre
of each eye's field
of view.
Adjust the brightness to suit the examination
you're about to perform.
In babies, it's best to start with a low
illumination, then gradually increase until you can see enough detail
without causing disturbance to the child.
In adults, start with a medium
brightness and spot size.
You need to use a condensing lens to see the
funders with a BIO.
There are different powers of lenses
with the most commonly used, 20 doctors, 28 or 30.
Different lenses create different fields of view and consequently different
degrees of magnification as illustrated here.
Like with any patient examination,
ensure you wash your hands and are wearing appropriate PPE.
Explain to the patient that you'll be
examining the back of the eye and that the bright light may be uncomfortable.
Make sure that they're
happy to proceed and answer any questions they may have.
Dialate the patient's pupils to enable
a full funders view.
A topical anesthetic can also be used to ensure the patient is comfortable
during the examination.
The patient should be examined ideally lying
supine or in a reclining chair.
Examining a baby may be challenging and you should
consider using old sucrose before the examination, swaddling the child, instilling
local anesthetic drops or using a speculum to facilitate a thorough examination.
When the patient is dilated, the room should be dimly lit to maximize contrast.
For this video we'll be keeping the lights on.
You should examine the patient in a
quite environment to allow a comfortable examination.
Stand at the head of the
patient, adjust the bed or chair height to ensure both you and the patient are
comfortable.
Angle the light source towards the patient's eye and examine the
red reflex.
Then use a condensing lens to bring the posterior pole into view.
You
can gently arrest your hand on the patient's forehead for stability.
Ensure that the
patient's eye is in line with your light source and condensing lens.
You will have
to move the lens to bring the funders into focus.
It takes practice to keep the funders in view
and to become comfortable finding the working distance of the lens.
You should be aware that
different lenses and patients will have different working distances.
It's important to have the
BIO condensing lens and the area of retina to be examined all aligned.
If you see shadows on the
edge of your view, it may mean that one of these are incorrectly aligned.
To avoid unwanted glare,
you can try tilting the lens as this may help to eliminate this.
Bring the posterior pole into view.
You should examine the optic disc and the
macular.
Adjust the brightness according to the quality of view and patient comfort.
On initial examination the lighter will be very bright for the patient and this
will settle once the retina is bleached in all four quadrants.
To view the peripheral retina, change the angulation by asking the patient to
look in the direction of the area to be examined.
You can move around the bed and
tilt your body to view the peripheral fundus.
To see the superior and inferior
fundus, you may find it easier to stand at the temporal side of the patient as
soon here.
Again, this skill takes practice.
You may find you keep losing your
view.
This is likely due to incorrect alignment of the BIO condensing lens and
the peripheral fundus.
If this happens, try to adjust the angle of examination
and ensure that you are in line correctly.
You should examine all quadrants of the fundus.
You should feel comfortable moving around the bed
and tilting your body to help your view.
You will likely need to keep the eyelid open
to maintain your view with your fingers.
If the patient struggles to maintain their direction of gaze,
you can use a fixation target
such as the patient's finger or thumb as shown here.
With slow indentation, the BIO can allow visualization
of the far periphery of the retina.
This technique brings the anterior retina into view.
It can be helpful to view the aurisorata
and look for peripheral retinal pathology,
such as anterior retinal tears,
that would otherwise be not visible on a regular examination.
You will require appropriate anesthetic drops
and an indenting instrument.
You should warn the patient that this may be uncomfortable.
To perform skeletal indentation,
position the patient as before.
You can indent directly onto the sclera or over the eyelids.
Ask the patient to look in the opposite area to be examined, allow the
indenter to rest
tangentially against the area to be indented, then ask the patient to look towards the area
to be examined and exert a gentle pressure.
This example shows the examination of the superior retina being examined.
The patient is asked to look downwards towards their feet.
The indenter is then placed on the superior eyelid and rolled.
Then the patient is asked to look upwards.
a gentle pressure is required.
This is a dynamic examination and the
indentor will be moved to observe the peripheral retina.
You should thank the patient and give them ample time to recover from the
examination before they send up.
Document your findings and inform the patient
of your conclusion if appropriate.
This completes the BIO fundus examination.
It's a challenging practical skill but with practice you will develop muscle
memory to help you maintain a clear view of the fundus.
We hope you found this video helpful, thank you very much for watching.